Part two: Escalation of Pain
When pain gets worse: Pinpointing the pain
Sometimes the pain can get worse
and spread
to different parts of your head and neck.
When this happens, it is important
to tell us exactly where it hurts.
That way,
we can give treatment that targets
the painful area to help make it better.
Pain in the Neck, Ear or Nerves:
Gabapentin
If the pain follows a nerve
and affects your neck, ears,
or other areas of the face,
we might give you a medicine
called gabapentin.
This medicine is specifically useful
in targeting nerve pain,
and it is not an opioid,
so it has fewer side effects.
Once we start gabapentin, we can adjust
the dose to help manage the level of pain.
Gabapentin can cause sleepiness or nausea,
so we recommend taking the medication
at night before bedtime to start with.
If tolerated well,
you can increase the dose
and also take it more throughout the day.
Using Opioid Pain Pills
For about half of the patients,
opioid pain medications might be needed
by the end of treatment.
These include liquid morphine rinses
or pills like hydrocodone or oxycodone.
We try to save these strong medicines
for when you really need them.
Don't hesitate to ask for them
if your pain is too much to handle.
We can help you find the right dose
to manage your pain.
We will discuss side effects and safety
of these medications in a separate video.
Getting Help from Pain Management
Specialists.
If you're trying lots of things
and still in pain,
we can get help from pain management
specialists.
Let us know
if your pain isn't getting better
and we can involve them sooner.
If you were already in pain
before starting treatment,
we can even get them involved right away.